<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-10-18T10:18:19+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Afzal Ahmad</title><subtitle>in love with robots</subtitle><author><name></name></author><entry><title type="html">ARLE</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/projects/arle.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ARLE" /><published>2019-10-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-10-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/projects/arle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/projects/arle.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Autonomous Robot for Library Enhancement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
This project is a part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QdKhtsYo7OM&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;4i Lab&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; initiative of IIT(Indian Institute of Technology) Guwahati to enable students to create novel solutions for real-world problems using state-of-the-art technology. I along with a group of students worked on the project to complete the first version of the robot capable of book identification and autonomous navigation inside the institute library. It is designed to help the library staff as well as the readers in efficient and immediate management of the library.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I worked on creating a path planning algoithm and integrating the ROS-based control pipeline. We used a 2d-lidar based mapping algorithm to create an initial map of the library environment. The robot is able to recognise the RFID of the book and guide the reader to the shelf. It uses a online path planner to avoid any static or dynamic obstacles such as other readers moving inside the library.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/51S_pQePftE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;teamImage&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;My Team&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;teamImage&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/4i_team.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:600px;height:400px;&quot; /&gt;  
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Afzal Ahmad</name></author><category term="documentation" /><category term="projects" /><category term="4i" /><category term="4i Labs" /><category term="library" /><category term="arle" /><category term="librarybot" /><summary type="html">Autonomous Robot for Library Enhancement This project is a part of the 4i Lab initiative of IIT(Indian Institute of Technology) Guwahati to enable students to create novel solutions for real-world problems using state-of-the-art technology. I along with a group of students worked on the project to complete the first version of the robot capable of book identification and autonomous navigation inside the institute library. It is designed to help the library staff as well as the readers in efficient and immediate management of the library. I worked on creating a path planning algoithm and integrating the ROS-based control pipeline. We used a 2d-lidar based mapping algorithm to create an initial map of the library environment. The robot is able to recognise the RFID of the book and guide the reader to the shelf. It uses a online path planner to avoid any static or dynamic obstacles such as other readers moving inside the library.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">HIVE</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/projects/hive.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="HIVE" /><published>2018-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/projects/hive</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/projects/hive.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intelligent Swarm System&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
I along with two undergraduate students worked on a swarm of robots under the guidance of Dr. Karuna Kalita at Indian Institute of Technology Guwahati. Hive (a name for collection of bees), is a group of autonomous robots designed to perform tasks in a collaborative and optimized manner. The robots are designed to search for objects in an indoor environment and assemble at a particular point. The focus of the project is on making a simple yet intelligent system of multiple robots that showcase Swarm Intelligence.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/hive-2.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:800px;height:350px;border-color: white&quot; border=&quot;4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is it a Swarm system or a multi-robot system ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
As per the definitions coined by Zhong-yang ZHENG in his paper on Swarm Intelligence, Hive can be considered a Swarm system. All the robots in Hive are independent and homogeneous in all senses. There is no Master-Slave correspondence. The software design is robust to the number of robots in the group thus making the system easily extensible.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;algorithms&quot;&gt;Algorithms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborative Search&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A modified form of Particle Swarm Optimisation algorithm is implemented to perform an optimised search of the environment.The robots search their neighbouring environment for a particular type of stimuli and store information for Mapping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rendezvous Algorithm&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/hive-3.png&quot; style=&quot;float:right;width:440px;height:330px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
A custom designed rendezvous algorithm is used for successful aggregation of robots. The range sensors search for other objects in a local area around the robot. The robot then moves towards the closest object found. The decision is updated continuously which helps the robot in differentiating between a fellow bot and a passive object.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The body of the robot was designed on SolidWorks CAD software and cut out of &lt;em&gt;4mm&lt;/em&gt; Plexi-glass sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Electronics&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/hive-4.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:right;width:300px;height:350px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The robot is powered by &lt;em&gt;ATmega328u Micro-controller&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Each of them is made of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2x Stepper DC motors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6x Ultrasonic range sensors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2x Motor driver modules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;demonstration&quot;&gt;Demonstration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;imgcap&quot;&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;thecap&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Testing the range sensors&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;350&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bafYjByexFc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;thecap&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Rendezvous demonstration&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;620px&quot; height=&quot;325px&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/POwtcVPyVss?rel=0&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;utoplay=1&amp;amp;loop=1&amp;amp;rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Afzal Ahmad</name></author><category term="documentation" /><category term="projects" /><category term="swarm" /><category term="hive" /><summary type="html">Intelligent Swarm System I along with two undergraduate students worked on a swarm of robots under the guidance of Dr. Karuna Kalita at Indian Institute of Technology Guwahati. Hive (a name for collection of bees), is a group of autonomous robots designed to perform tasks in a collaborative and optimized manner. The robots are designed to search for objects in an indoor environment and assemble at a particular point. The focus of the project is on making a simple yet intelligent system of multiple robots that showcase Swarm Intelligence.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ASROA</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/projects/asroa.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASROA" /><published>2018-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/projects/asroa</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/projects/asroa.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;autonomous-snake-robot-for-obstacle-avoidance&quot;&gt;Autonomous Snake Robot for Obstacle Avoidance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nature has inspired many robot designs. Some of the best examples include &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.mit.edu/2015/cheetah-robot-lands-running-jump-0529&quot;&gt;Cheetah&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bostondynamics.com/wildcat&quot;&gt;WildCat&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://biorobotics.ri.cmu.edu/projects/modsnake/&quot;&gt;Modular Snake Robot&lt;/a&gt;. Learning about the environment and reacting to it has been a major part of research on these robots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is an attempt to make a simple-to-build snake robot that can learn to avoid obstacles. I along with another undergrad worked on this project under the guidance of &lt;strong&gt;Dr. Prithwijit Guha&lt;/strong&gt; at Indian Institute of Technology Guwahati. You can read the detailed report &lt;a href=&quot;#pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-problem-statment&quot;&gt;The problem statment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
	The snake has several types of moving techniques including side-winding, serpentine and rectilinear motion. We focus our work on serpentine motion as it can use obstacles as suppport to move along. The serpentine motion is goverened by a controller that takes in several parameters as input. Given these parameters one can generate a variety of motion from the snake. But these parameters have to be manually tuned for a certain type of motion. Taking inspiration from a real snake, we try to move the snake through an obstacle filled map. This will require the snake to change it's motion depending upon the sensor data from the environment. We proppose that this sensor data along with the knowledge of the previous move can be used to predict the upcoming moves for the robot. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;approach-used&quot;&gt;Approach used&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
	As there was no open source design available for our snake robot, we start our work with designing a simulated snake robot for training and testing our algorithms. We designed our robot using V-rep simulation software. We further tune the simulated robot by changing the design parameters. 
	We also need a global path planner to achieve autonomous navigation in an obstacle map. We use watershed algorithm to solve this problem. The approach is similar to vornoi diagrams that generates several possible paths through a given map. These are then used by the snake robot to generate data.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/asroa-2.png&quot; style=&quot;float:right;width:350px;height:300px;border-color: white&quot; border=&quot;4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We propose the following approaches to design a predictive model for our robot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finding correlation between sensor data and control parameters of the serpenoid curve using k-means clustering.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using ARMA model to predict the control parameters by treating it as a time series.(signal processing based approach)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using a recurrent neural network to predict control parameters (machine learning based approach)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;simulation&quot;&gt;Simulation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
	The snake and it's environment is designed on the Virtual Robot Experimentation Platform (V-rep). The design of the robot is based on the available material and components required to make a real robot. This will make it easier to reproduce the test results on a real snake robot. 
	&lt;div style=&quot;float:left;margin:0 10px 5px 0;&quot;&gt;
		&lt;iframe width=&quot;441&quot; height=&quot;278&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-zKmTJUTa3k&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
		&lt;/iframe&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
The snake robot uses serpenoid curve as its control scheme. This serpenoid curve is used to generate serpentine motion in the robot. The serpenoid curve was originally introduced by &lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=562623&quot;&gt;Hirose&lt;/a&gt; to approximate the the serpentine motion of a snake. We use the modified serpenoid curve.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;path-planning&quot;&gt;Path Planning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/asroa-3.png&quot; style=&quot;float:right;width:350px;height:300px;border-color: white;margin:0 0 0 10px;&quot; border=&quot;4&quot; /&gt;  
	We have used an image segmenting algorithm called watershed algorithm to segment the entire arena into sectors. The boundaries of these sectors have been taken as possible paths for the robot. Further details are mentioned in the report.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lstm-model&quot;&gt;LSTM Model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From our observaton made during the simualtion of the snake robot, we found that the the “c” value or the heading direction of the robot depends upon the previous configuration of the robot and the sensor data of the present time-stamp. Thus, we try to design a recurrent neural network using an LSTM cell to predict the “c” value from the sensor values and control paramters of previous time-stamp. We use a single layer of 50 neurons, each nueron being an LSTM cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Input feature vector: 17 sensor values and “c” value from previous time-stamp 
Output of network: “c” value for current time-stamp.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Results:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Trainig Loss: 0.0019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Testing Loss: 0.0025&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results suggest that an LSTM model can be used for this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;demonstration&quot;&gt;Demonstration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;imgcap&quot;&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;thecap&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Autonomous navigation using path planning&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;441&quot; height=&quot;278&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/W7V0BaGdjgE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;pdf&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe class=&quot;scribd_iframe_embed&quot; title=&quot;asroa&quot; src=&quot;https://www.scribd.com/embeds/385489123/content?start_page=1&amp;amp;view_mode=scroll&amp;amp;access_key=key-pd7T40nAx8ISK9CaSAvZ&amp;amp;show_recommendations=true&quot; data-auto-height=&quot;false&quot; data-aspect-ratio=&quot;0.7068965517241379&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; id=&quot;doc_57066&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Afzal Ahmad</name></author><category term="documentation" /><category term="projects" /><category term="snake-robot" /><summary type="html">Autonomous Snake Robot for Obstacle Avoidance</summary></entry></feed>