<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>Afzal Ahmad</title>
		<description>in love with robots</description>
		<link></link>
		<atom:link href="/rss-feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>ARLE</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Afzal Ahmad</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Autonomous Robot for Library Enhancement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
This project is a part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QdKhtsYo7OM&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;4i Lab&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; initiative of IIT(Indian Institute of Technology) Guwahati to enable students to create novel solutions for real-world problems using state-of-the-art technology. I along with a group of students worked on the project to complete the first version of the robot capable of book identification and autonomous navigation inside the institute library. It is designed to help the library staff as well as the readers in efficient and immediate management of the library.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I worked on creating a path planning algoithm and integrating the ROS-based control pipeline. We used a 2d-lidar based mapping algorithm to create an initial map of the library environment. The robot is able to recognise the RFID of the book and guide the reader to the shelf. It uses a online path planner to avoid any static or dynamic obstacles such as other readers moving inside the library.
&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/projects/arle.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/projects/arle.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>HIVE</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Afzal Ahmad</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intelligent Swarm System&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
I along with two undergraduate students worked on a swarm of robots under the guidance of Dr. Karuna Kalita at Indian Institute of Technology Guwahati. Hive (a name for collection of bees), is a group of autonomous robots designed to perform tasks in a collaborative and optimized manner. The robots are designed to search for objects in an indoor environment and assemble at a particular point. The focus of the project is on making a simple yet intelligent system of multiple robots that showcase Swarm Intelligence.
&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/projects/hive.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/projects/hive.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>ASROA</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Afzal Ahmad</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;autonomous-snake-robot-for-obstacle-avoidance&quot;&gt;Autonomous Snake Robot for Obstacle Avoidance&lt;/h2&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/projects/asroa.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/projects/asroa.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
